Xavier University Acquisition of Edgecliff College records
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
Xavier University Acquisition of Edgecliff College records
1967-1989
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)
1 linear feet (3 boxes)
This is a collection of correspondence and related documents concerning the relationship of Edgecliff College and Xavier University from the Office of the Provost. The subject content deals chiefly with negotiations on the sale of Edgecliff to Xavier, on subsequent Xavier programming on the Edgecliff campus, and the eventual sale of the Edgecliff property by Xavier.
XUA-48
History of Xavier University Acquisiton of Edgecliff College
Xavier University purchased a three year option to purchase the Edgecliff College property in 1980. In 1983 the purchase was completed. In 1987 Xavier University sold the Edgecliff property but incorporated many of the Edgecliff academic programs into its curriculum.
Originally called Our Lady of Cincinnati College at its founding in 1935 by the Sisters of Mercy, the college educated young women exclusively until 1970 when it opened its classrooms to men and adopted a new name, Edgecliff College. On July 1, 1980 Xavier University announced that it had purchased from the Sisters of Mercy a three year option to buy the Edgecliff campus property by June 30, 1983. Edgecliff College then became known as Edgecliff College of Xavier University, the fourth undergraduate college at Xavier University. In the spring of 1983 Xavier completed the purchase of the Edgecliff property from the Sisters of Mercy. In April 1987 Xavier University sold the Edgecliff property. Academic programming was transferred to the main Xavier campus that year. Edgecliff's departments of art, music, and theatre arts joined the College of Arts and Sciences, while its departments of nursing and social work were incorporated into Xavier's new College of Professional Studies.
Scope and Content
This collection gives a picture of the negotiations leading to the purchase of Edgecliff College by Xavier University and subsequent transitional activities during and after the purchase process. Included in the collection are correspondence files of various academic vice presidents. Both the purchase agreement of 1983 and the sale agreement of 1987 are included in this collection.
Not specified
Statement of Arrangement
The collection is arranged in these general categories:
Correspondence Files
Transitional Topics (Committees, Academic Programs, etc.)
Legal Documents
Restrictions on Access
Restricted access. Please contact the Xavier University Archives staff.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from the Office of the Administrative Vice President, XUA2008-11.
Custodial History
These records were transferred to University Archives from the Office of the Administrative Vice President and principal assistant to the president (transfer, XUA2008-11). This office currently manages property acquisition for the university. Much of the correspondence files was originally held in the Office of the Xavier University Academic Vice President, know known as the Office of the Provost and Chief Academic Officer.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects:
Edgecliff College; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Administration
Organizations/Corporations:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Office of the Provost and Chief Academic Officer
Detailed Description of The Collection
- Edgecliff Related Correspondence of Xavier Academic Vice Presidents (Brennan; Minahan; Fortin), 1967-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  This is a correspondence file maintained by various Xavier University Academic Vice Presidents and relating to Xavier University's relationship with Edgecliff College and the eventual acquisition of Edgecliff by Xavier. Included in the file is correspondence, with related documents, from and to Francis C. Brennan, S.J., Dr. John P. Minahan and Dr. Roger Fortin. Correspondence of Dr. Roger Fortin acting as Dean of Edgecliff College of Xavier University is also found.
- Edgecliff Negotiations Correspondence File (Brennan), 1977 May 1; 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 8-14, Box 2, Folder 1)
  This correspondence file of Francis C. Brennan, S.J., Xavier University Academic Vice President, deals with the negotiations between officials of Edgecliff College and Xavier University regarding the acquisition of Edgecliff by Xavier University. Included are copies of correspondence of the Xavier University president Robert W. Mulligan, S.J.. Related documents are included in the file.
- College of Professional Studies Xavier University Academic Vice Presidents Correspondence, 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Edgecliff Task Force, 1981-1983; undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  The mission of the Edgecliff Task Force was to make a recommendation to the Xavier Board of Trustees concerning "finalizing the Edgecliff College acquisition...More specifically, ....to address...1) the feasibility of increasing the enrollment in existing programs and developing new enrollments in new credit and non-credit programs on the Edgecliff Campus; 2) the feasibility of developing additional revenue through summer rental of Edgecliff facilities; 3) the cost and feasibility of reproducing current Edgecliff programs on the main campus (as a means of assessing the value of Edgecliff programs within the University); 4) the feasibility of alternate ...methods of meeting all or part of the acquisition costs." (see Currie memo of 9/29/1982 to the Task Force)
  The Xavier University Archives also has materials on the Edgecliff Campus Coordinating Committee found in XUA-36, Xavier University inactive committee records (Box 1, Folder 8).
- Edgecliff Outreach Task Force, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  This was a committee headed by Robert W. Schmidt, S.J.. Its purpose was to foster relationships between Edgecliff College and the local community. Correspondence originated in the office files of Academic Vice President Dr. John Minahan.
- Edgecliff Negotiations: Clippings and Correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Edgecliff Property Sale: Memos to the Xavier Community, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Tuition Remissions Xavier Academic Vice Presidents Correspondence File, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Edgecliff College Purchase Agreement and Related Documents, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4-7)
- Edgecliff Property Sale Agreement and Related Documents, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 8-10)